Register of the Irwin T. and Shirley Holtzman collection, 1899-2010
Hoover Institution Archives
- Isaac Babel File, 1913-2002.
  - Reference, 1926-1998.
    - Lewanski, Richard C., The Slavic Literatures, New York, 1971 (Folder 113: 2)
      (IV.12)
    - Stsenaristy sovetskogo khudozhestvennogo kino, 1917-1967, Moscow, 1972 (Folder 113: 3)
      (IV.13)
    - List of books subject to Soviet censorship, 1973. (Folder 113: 4)
      Photocopy (IV.14)
    - Vospominaniia i dnevniki xviii-xx vv., Moscow, 1976 (Box-folder 114: 1)
      (IV.15)
    - Index to Russian Literature Triquarterly, 1971-1976, Ann Arbor, 1978 (Folder 114: 2)
      (IV.16)
    - Vstrechi s proshlym, Moscow
      - 1975 edition (Folder 114: 3)
        (IV.17)
      - 1978 edition (Folder 114: 4)
        (IV.18)
      - 1982 edition (Box-folder 115: 1)
        (IV.19)
      - 1984 edition (Folder 115: 2)
        (IV.20)
    - Proizvedennia sovetskikh pisatelei v perevodakh na inostrannye iazyki, 1976-1980, Moscow, 1981 (Folder 115: 3)
      (IV.21)
    - Proizvedennia sovetskikh pisatelei v perevodakh na inostrannye iazyki, 1981-1985, Moscow, 1986 (Folder 115: 4)
      (IV.22)
    - Spector, Uzer M., "Posviashchaetsia Isaaku Babeliu," Rossiiskaia knizhnaia palata bibliografiia, no. 2 (258), 1993 March/April (Folder 115: 5)
      (IV.23)
    - Dokumenty po istorii i kul'ture evreev, Moscow, 1997 (Box-folder 116: 1)
      (IV.24)
    - "Schast'e literatury": Gosudarstvo i pisateli, 1925-1938: Dokumenty, Moscow, 1997 (Folder 116: 2)
      (IV.25)
    - Pasternak, Boris, Pis'ma k roditeliam I cestram, volume two, Stanford, 1998 (Folder 116: 3)
      (IV.26)
  - Life, 1926-1996.; See also Oversize and miscellaneous materials, box 147
    Correspondence, monographs, and other materials, relating to Babel.
    - Telegram from Babel to the editorial board of Znamia vashentseva, 1926 December 10 (Folder 116: 4)
      (V.1)
    - Postcard from Babel to Mr. Savich, 1933 December 3. (Folder 116: 5)
      Includes photocopy of English translation, n.d. (V.2)
    - Envelope and picture, delivered by Isaac Babel to his nephew, Vasily Livanov, 1935 (Folder 116: 6)
      (V.3)
    - Letter from Babel to unknown addressee, 1935 December 5 (Folder 116: 7)
      (V.4).
      Includes photocopy of a letter to Toby Holtzman from Dmitry Urnov, with English translation and explication of Babel's letter, 1998 August 3
    - Envelope addressed by Babel to Solomon M. Mikhoels, 1935 (Folder 116: 8)
      (V.5).
      Includes description by Alex Rabinovich of significance of Mikhoels, n.d.
    - Letter from Babel to copyright office, 1936 December 21. (Folder 116: 9)
      Includes photocopy of English translation, n.d. (V.6)
    - Correspondence and other materials, relating to a sale of a supposed Babel manuscript by Sotheby's, 1993. (Folder 116: 10)
      Includes a letter addressed to Toby Holtzman, 1994 January 22 (V.7)
    - Pisateli: Avtobiografii I portrety sovremennykh russkikh prozaikov, Moscow, 1926 (Box-folder 117: 1)
      (V.8)
    - Ogonëk catalog, with description of Babel, 1926 (Folder 117: 2)
      (V.9).
      Folder includes English translation, n.d.
    - International Literature, no. 1, 1932 (Folder 117: 3)
      (V.10)
    - Venevitinov, D. V., Polnoe sobranie sochinenii, Moscow/Leningrad, 1934 (Folder 117: 4)
      (V.11)
    - Gogol, Nikolai V., Mertvye dushi, Moscow, 1934 (Folder 117: 5)
      (V.12).
      Inscribed by Babel
    - Malraux, André, La condition humaine, Paris, 1933 (Folder 117: 6)
      (V.13).
      Inscribed by Malraux to Babel
    - Pervyi vsesoiuznyi s'ezd sovetskikh pisatelei 1934, Moscow (Box-folder 118: 1)
      Includes transcript of Babel's remarks, pp. 278-280 (V.14)
    - Literature of the Peoples of the USSR, nos. 7-8, 1934 (Folder 118: 2)
      (V.15)
    - Desiat' rokiv odes'kogo teatru revoliutsii, Odessa, 1936 (Folder 118: 3)
      (V.16)
    - Babel, Isaac, "With Our Father Makhno: An Episode of the Russian Civil War," Contemporary Poetry and Prose, 1936 December 8 (Folder 118: 4)
      (V.17).
      Title only appears printed in journal, with space for text left blank
    - Ladygina-Kost', N. N., U 'mysliashchkh'' loshadei, 1914 (Folder 118: 5)
      (V.18)
    - Gibian, George, Interval of Freedom: Soviet Literature during the Thaw, 1954-1957, St. Paul, Minn., 1960 (Folder 118: 6)
      (V.19)
    - Babel', Isaak, Racconti proibiti e lettere intime, Milan, 1961. (Box-folder 119: 1)
      Italian translation of selected stories and letters (V.20)
    - Fomin, F. T., Zapiski starogo chekista, Moscow, 1964 (Folder 119: 2)
      (V.21)
    - Isaac Babel: The Lonely Years, 1925-1939, New York, 1964.
      English translation of unpublished stories and letters
      - Hardcover edition (Folder 119: 3)
        (V.22)
      - Paperback edition (Folder 119: 4)
        (V.23)
    - Isaac Babel: The Lonely Years, 1925-1939, Boston, 1995 (Box-folder 120: 1)
      (V.24).
      Includes a new introduction by Nathalie Babel
    - Babel', Isaak, "Zabytye rasskazy," Znamia, no. 8, 1964 (Folder 120: 2)
      (V.25)
    - Munblit, Georgi, "Reminiscences of Babel," Soviet Literature, no. 1, 1965 (Folder 120: 3)
      (V.26).
      Also includes a selection from Babel's letters
    - Conquest, Robert, The Great Terror: Stalin's Purge of the Thirties, New York, 1969 (Folder 120: 4)
      (V.27)
    - Conquest, Robert, The Great Terror: A Reassessment, New York, 1990 (Box-folder 121: 1)
      (V.28)
    - Guidorizzi, Ernesto, Pasternák ed altri saggi, Naples, 1970 (Folder 121: 2)
      (V.29)
    - Stroud, Nicholas, "The Art of Mystification: The 'Prehistoric' Babel," Russian Literature Triquarterly, no. 13, 1975 Fall (Folder 121: 3)
      (V.30)
    - Kazin, Alfred, New York Jew, New York, 1978 (Folder 121: 4)
      (V.31)
    - Khinkulov, Leonid, Literaturni zustrichi, Kiev, 1989 (Box-folder 122: 1)
      (V.32)
    - Kranoshchekova, E. A., Khudozhestvennyi mir Vsevoloda Ivanova, Moscow, 1980 (Folder 122: 2)
      (V.33)
    - Gilboa, Yehoshua, A Language Silenced: The Suppression of Hebrew Literature and Culture in the Soviet Union, New York, 1982 (Folder 122: 3)
      (V.34)
    - Lottman, Herbert R., The Left Bank: Writers, Artists, and Politics from the Popular Front to the Cold War, Boston, 1982 (Folder 122: 4)
      (V.35)
    - Gereben, Ágnes, "Miért hallgatott Iszaak Babel?," Új irás, no. 5, 1983 May (Folder 122: 5)
      (V.36)
    - Proffer, Carl R., The Widows of Russia and Other Writings, Ann Arbor, 1987 (Box-folder 123: 1)
      (V.37)
    - Beizer, Mikhail, The Jews of St. Petersburg: Excursions through a Noble Past, Philadelphia, 1989 (Folder 123: 2)
      (V.38)
    - Zlenko, Grigorii, 3 polony lit, Odessa, 1990 (Folder 123: 3)
      (V.39)
    - Gereben, Ágnes, Iszaak Babel ismeretlen naplója, Budapest, 1989 (Folder 123: 4)
      (V.40)
    - Babel, Isaac, Tagebuch 1920, Berlin, 1990 (Folder 123: 5)
      (V.41)
    - Babel, Isaac, 1920 Diary, New Haven, Conn.
      - Galley proofs, 1995 (Folder 123: 6)
        (V.42)
      - Hardback edition, 1995 (Box-folder 124: 1)
        (V.43)
      - Paperback edition, 1995 (Folder 124: 2)
        (V.44)
      - Paperback reprinting, 2002 (Folder 124: 3)
        (V.45)
    - Gereben, Ágnes, Babel világa, Budapest, 1990 (Folder 124: 4)
      (V.46)
    - Moi vek, moi druz'ia i podrugi: Vospominaniia Mariengofa, Shershenevicha, Gruzinova, Moscow, 1990 (Folder 124: 5)
      (V.47)
    - Geizer, M. M., Solomon Mikhoels, Moscow, 1990 (Box-folder 125: 1)
      (V.48)
    - Friedberg, Maurice, How Things Were Done in Odessa, Boulder, Co., 1991 (Folder 125: 2)
      (V.49)
    - Vaksberg, Arkady, Stalin's Prosecutor: The Life of Andrei Vyshinsky, New York, 1991 (Folder 125: 3)
      (V.50)
    - Curtis, J. A. E., Manuscripts Don't Burn: Mikhail Bulgakov, a Life in Letters and Diaries, Woodstock, N.Y., 1992 (Folder 125: 4)
      (V.51)
    - Brown, Deming, The Last Years of Soviet Russian Literature, Cambridge, England, 1993 (Folder 125: 5)
      (V.52)
    - Turan, Kenneth, "Isaac Babel," The Pakyn Treger, no. 23, 1996 Winter (Box-folder 126: 1)
      (V.53)
    - Garrard, John, The Bones of Berdichev: The Life and Fate of Vasily Grosssman, New York, 1996 (Folder 126: 2)
      (V.54)
    - Friedberg, Maurice, Literary Translation in Russia: A Cultural History, 1997 (Folder 126: 3)
      (V.55)
    - Lincoln, W. Bruce, Between Heaven and Hell: The Story of a Thousand Years of Artistic Life in Russia, 1998 (Folder 126: 4)
      (V.56)
    - Cohen, Rich, Tough Jews, New York, 1998 (Box-folder 127: 1)
      (V.57)
    - Fleishman, Lazar, "Ob odnom neraskrytom 'prestuplenii' Babelia," Poetika istoriia literatury lingvistika, Moscow, 1999 (Folder 127: 2)
      (V.58)
    - Conquest, Robert, Reflections on a Ravaged Century, London, 2000 (Folder 127: 3)
      (V.59)
    - Shrayer, Maxim D., Russian Poet Soviet Jew: The Legacy of Eduard Bagritskii, Lanham, Maryland, 2000 (Box-folder 128: 1)
      (V.60)
    - Khazan, Vladimir, Osobennyi evreisko-russkii vozdukh, Moscow, 2001 (Folder 128: 2)
      (V.61)
    - Jansen, Marc and Nikita Petrov, Stalin's Loyal Executioner: People's Commissar Nikolai Ezhov, 1895-1940, Stanford, Ca., 2002 (Folder 128: 3)
      (V.62)
    - Babenko, Pëtr M., A. E. Iakir, Moscow, 1963 (Folder 128: 4)
      (V.64)
    - Nikulin, Lev, Tukhachevskii, Moscow, 1964 (Folder 128: 5)
      (V.65)
    - V. N. Shiriaev, ed., V boiakh rozhdennaia, Rostov—on-Don, 1969 (Folder 128: 6)
      (V.66)
    - Budennyi, S. M., Pervaia konnaia na donu, Rostov-on-Don, 1967 (Folder 128: 7)
      (V.67)
    - Eremin, Dmitrii, V te bradtsatye gody, Moscow, 1971 (Box-folder 129: 1)
      (V.68)
    - Leonova, M. F., Dmitrii Pokrass, Moscow, 1981 (Folder 129: 2)
      (V.69)
    - Legendarnyi polkovodets: Sbornik sopominanii o G. I. Kotovskom, Kiev, 1981 (Folder 129: 3)
      (V.70)
    - Gusev-Orenburgskii, Bagrovaia kniga: Pogromy 1919-1920 gg. na Ukraine, New York, 1983 (Folder 129: 4)
      (V.71)
    - Shentalinskii, Vitalii, "Proshu menia vyslushat'...," Ogonëk, no. 39, 1989 September 23-30 (Folder 129: 5)
      (V.72)
    - Frydman, Anne, "The Murder of Isaac Babel," Dissent, 1991 Winter (Folder 129: 6)
      (V.73)
    - Kuchment, Mark and Joshua Rubenstein, "A Writer in Peril: The Last Days of Isaac Babel," Bostonia, 1990 July/August (Folder 129: 7)
      (V.74)
    - Shentalinskii, Vitalii, "Babel: Lies, Confessions and Denials," Index on Censorship, 1991 August/September (Folder 129: 8)
      (V.75)
    - Slutskii, Boris, "Kak ia opisyval imushchestvo u Babelia," Literaturnaia Gazeta, special issue, no. 9, 1991 (Folder 129: 9)
      (V.76)
    - Shentalinskii, Vitalii, "Proshu menia vyslushat'...," Vozvrashchenie, no. 1, 1991 (Folder 129: 10)
      (V.77)
    - Chentalinski, Vitali, La parole ressuscitée: Dans les archives littéraires du K.G.B., Paris, 1993 (Box-folder 130: 1)
      (V.78).
      French translation of Russian book by Vitalii Shentalinskii, folder 3 below
    - Babel, Isaac, You Must Know Everything, New York, 1980 (Folder 130: 2)
      (V.78C)
    - Shentalinskii, Vitalii, Raby svobody: V literaturnykh arkhivakh KGB, Moscow, 1995 (Folder 130: 3)
      (V.79)
    - Shentalinsky, Vitaly, The KGB's Literary Archive, London, 1996 (Folder 130: 4)
      (V.80).
      Photocopy of chapter on Babel, from English translation of Russian book above, folder 3. Includes letter to Irwin Holtzman from Fred (?), 1996 June 18
    - Shentalinsky, Vitaly, Arrested Voices: Resurrecting the Disappeared Writers of the Soviet Regime, New York, 1993 (Box-folder 131: 1)
      (V.81).
      American edition of book described above
    - Povartso, Sergei, Prichina smerti-rasstrel, Moscow, 1996 (Folder 131: 2)
      (V.[left unnumbered by collector])
  - Memoirs, 1961-2002.
    Printed copies of monographs and serial issues, relating to the recollections by others of Babel and his milieu
    - Eisenstein, Segei M., Izbrannyee proezvedeniia v shesti tomakh, Moscow, 1964
      (VI.1)
      - Volume one (Folder 131: 3)
      - Volume two (Folder 131: 4)
      - Volume three (Box-folder 132: 1)
      - Volume four (Folder 132: 2)
    - Eisenstein, Sergei M., Immoral Memories: An Autobiography, Boston, 1983 (Folder 132: 3)
      (VI.2).
      English translation of part of Russian book listed above
    - Ehrenburg, Ilya, "Recollections of Isaac Babel," Two Cities, 1961 Winter (Box-folder 133: 1)
      (VI.3)
    - Ehrenburg, Ilya, First Years of Revolution, 1918-1921, London, 1962 (Folder 133: 2)
      (VI.4)
    - Ehrenburg, Ilya, Memoirs: 1921-1941, Cleveland, 1964 (Folder 133: 3)
      (VI.5)
    - Goldberg, Anatol, Ilya Ehrenburg: Writing, Politics and the Art of Survival, London, 1984 (Folder 133: 4)
      (VI.6)
    - Nikulin, Lev, Gody nashei zhizni: Vospominaniia I portrety, Moscow, 1966 (Box-folder 134: 1)
      (VI.7)
    - Paustovsky, Konstantin, Years of Hope, New York, 1969 (Folder 134: 2)
      (VI.8)
    - Paustovsky, Konstantin, The Restless Years, London, 1974 (Folder 134: 3)
      (VI.9)
    - Katayev, Valentin, The Grass of Oblivion, New York, 1969 (Folder 134: 4)
      (VI.10)
    - Annenkov, Iurii, Dnevnik moikh vstrech, n.d. (Box-folder 135: 1)
      (VI.11)
    - Munblit, Georgii, Rasskazy o pisateliakh, Moscow, 1976 (Folder 135: 2)
      (VI.12)
    - I. Babel': Vospominania sovremennikhov, Moscow, 1972. (Folder 135: 3)
      Two copies (VI.13, VI.14)
    - Souvarine, Boris, "Last Conversations with Isaac Babel," Dissent, 1981 Summer (Folder 135: 4)
      (VI.15)
    - Munblit, Georgii, Davnie vremena, Moscow, 1983 (Folder 135: 5)
      (VI.16)
    - Boris Livanov, Moscow, 1983 (Folder 135: 6)
      (VI.17)
    - Ivanova, Tamara V., Moi sovremenniki, kakimi ia ikh znala, Moscow, 1984 (Box-folder 136: 1)
      (VI.18)
    - Zakushniak, Aleksandr Ia., Vechera rasskaza, Moscow, 1984 (Folder 136: 2)
      (VI.19)
    - Vospominaniia o Babele, Moscow, 1989. (Folder 136: 3)
      Two copies (VI.20, VI.21)
    - Razgon, Lev, Nepridumannoe: Povest' v rasskazakh, Moscow, 1989 (Folder 136: 4)
      (VI.22)
    - Chukovskii, Kornei I., Dnevnik, 1901-1929, Moscow, 1991 (Folder 136: 5)
      (VI.23)
    - Piroshkowa, Antonina, Ich wünsche Ihnen Heiterkeit, Berlin, 1993 (Box-folder 137: 1)
      (VI.24)
    - Pirozhkova, Antonina, At His Side: The Last Years of Isaac Babel, South Royalton, Vermont, 1994
      - Typescript of translation by Anne Frydman and Robert Busch, originally entitled "Years at His Side" (Folder 137: 2)
        (VI.25).
        Includes letter to Irwin Holtzman from Robert Busch, 1994 September 29
      - Proof (Folder 137: 3)
        (VI.26)
      - Hardback edition (Folder 137: 4)
        (VI.27)
      - Paperback edition (Folder 137: 5)
        (VI.28)
    - Lesser, Alexander, "Believers and Victims," The Jerusalem Report, 1992 December 17. (Folder 137: 6)
      Review of Pirozhkova memoir (VI.29)
    - Pirožkòva, Antonina, Al suo fianco: Gli ultimi anni di Isaàk Bàbel', Milano, 1998 (Folder 137: 7)
      (VI.30)
    - Pirozhkova, Antonina, Be-tsido: Ha-shanim ha-aharaonot shel Isak Babel, Tel Aviv, 1999. (Box-folder 138: 1)
      (VI.31)
    - Piroshkova, Antonina, Set let s Isaakom Babelem, New York, 2001 (Folder 138: 2)
      (VI.32).
      Original Russian text of memoir published above in English, German, Italian, and Hebrew
  - Art, 1935-2002.; See also Oversize and miscellaneous materials, box 148
    Art works, article, drawing, lithograph, monographs, photographs, and other items, listed according to order established by collector, and all (with two exceptions) relating to Babel or his writings.
    - Lit-oratory, Moscow, 1935 (Folder 138: 3)
      (VII.1).
      Includes a caricature of Babel
    - Goffmeister, Adolf, Sharzhi, Moscow, 1935 (Folder 138: 4)
      (VII.2).
      Censored edition, omitting drawing of Karl Radek. Includes caricature of Babel
    - Bol'shevistskaia pechat', no. 10, 1936 (Folder 138: 5)
      (VII.3).
    - Levine, David, Pens and Needles, Boston, 1969 (Folder 138: 6)
      (VII.4).
    - Arkhangel'skii, Aleksandr, G., On Babel, Gladkov, Zharov, Zorich, Zorich, Zoshchenko, Inber, Klychkov... Iowa City, Iowa, 1976 (Folder 138: 7)
      (VII.5).
      In English and Russian. Includes caricature and parody of Babel
    - Vladimir Alekseevich Milashevskii, 1893-1976, Moscow, 1978 (Folder 138: 8)
      (VII.6).
      Folder also includes a print (VII.7) depicting the portrait of Babel appearing in this book
    - Fedorov, Georgii, Meer Aksel'rod, Moscow, 1982 (Box-folder 139: 1)
      (VII.8).
      Folder also contains a color print depicting the original artwork used for a black-and-white illustration appearing in this book
    - Livingstone, Marco, Kitaj, London, 1994 (Folder 139: 2)
      (VII.9, VII.10).
      Folder includes a print and a transparency of a Kitaj painting, depicting Babel on horseback, which is reproduced in this book
    - Spektor, U. M., "Illiustrirovannye izdaniia I. E. Babelia, 1926-1934," Panorama iskusstv, no. 8, 1985 (Folder 139: 3)
      (VII.11).
      Article concerning the illustrations used in Russian publications of Babel's writings. Folder includes entire serial issue
    - Ehrenburg, Ilya G., Kniga dlia vzroslykh, Moscow, 1992 (Folder 139: 4)
      (VII.12).
    - Pack, Susan, Film Posters of the Russian Avant-Garde, Köln, Germany (Folder 139: 5)
      (VII.13).
      Includes a reproduction of a poster advertising a film for which Babel wrote the screenplay
    - Rats, Mark, Staraia detskaia knizhka: 1900-1930-e gody, Moscow, 1997 (Box-folder 140: 1)
      (VII.14).
      Contains a reproduction of one illustration for a Babel story
    - Play money from Odessa, n.d. (Folder 140: 2)
      (VII.15).
      One bill includes Babel in its depiction of authors from Odessa
    - Katalog vystavki proizvedenii khudozhnika V. A. Milashevskogo, Saratov, 1979 (Folder 140: 3)
      (VII.16).
      Contains no material relating to Babel
    - Russian postcard with stamp depicting Babel, and with illustration of a Babel story, 1994 (Folder 140: 4)
      (VII.17)
    - Two prints depicting costume and set designs for a film based on a story by Babel, 1989 (Folder 140: 5)
      (VII.18).
      Folder includes clipping about the designer, Julia Belominsky
    - Catalog for an exhibit of ink drawings by Aleksandr Zapolinskii (Folder 140: 6)
      (VII.19).
      Folder includes one signed original, a portrait of Babel
    - Letter and photocopies relating to the offer for sale of drawings by Grigorii G. Filippovski, 2002 (Folder 140: 7)
      (VII.20)
    - Lithograph by Yuri Kuper depicting a character from one of Babel's stories, c. 1970 (Folder 140: 8)
      (VII.29)
    - Manuscript folder, n.d. (Folder 140: 9)
      (VII.30)
      Item has no direct relation to Babel, but is of a type commonly used by Russian writers in Babel's time
  - Audio, video, film, 1925-2002.; See also Oversize and miscellaneous materials, box 147, for one recording
    Prints and recordings, mostly relating to Babel's life, and listed in order established by the collector.
    - "Chetaet Dmitrii Zhuravlev," Soviet Union, n.d. (Folder 140: 10)
      One vinyl sound recording of Dmitrii Zhuravlev reading stories by Babel. In Russian
    - "Isaak Babel – Rasskazy,", n.d. (Folder 140: 11)
      (VIII.4).
      One audio cassette with a recording of stories by Isaac Babel, n.d. In Russian
    - "I. Babel': Zakat, Kak eto delalos' v Odesse, Korol', Froim Grach," Russia, 1998 (Folder 140: 12)
      (VIII.5).
      One compact disc recording of Veniamin Smekhov reading stories by Babel. In Russian
    - Ostrovskii, Georgii L., Odessa, more, kino, Odessa, 1989 (Box-folder 141: 1)
      (VIII.6).
      Printed copy of autobiography of film director
    - Heil, Jerry, "Isaak Babel' and His Film-Work," Russian Literature, vol. XXVII, 1990 (Folder 141: 2)
      (VIII.7).
      Photocopy of serial issue
    - One videotape recording of a documentary on Babel, c. 1990 (Folder 141: 3)
      (VIII.8).
      In German
    - One videotape recording of a BBC documentary on Babel, 1991 (Folder 141: 4)
      (VIII.10).
      In English
    - "Bindiuzhnik I Korol',", c. 1989 (Folder 141: 5)
      (VIII.11).
      Videotape recording of a film based on a Babel story. In Russian
    - "Zakat," New York, 1990 (Box-folder 142: 1)
      (VIII.12).
      Two videotape recordings of a film based on a play by Babel. In Russian
    - "Chapaev,", 1994 (Folder 142: 2)
      (VIII.13).
      One videoptape recording of a 1925 Russian film whose screenplay is attributed, in part, to Babel
    - Furmanov, Dmitri, Chapaev, Westport, Conn., 1973 (Folder 142: 3)
      (VIII.14).
      English translation of Russian novel upon which the above film is based
    - "Manuscripts Don't Burn," Netherlands, 1997 (Folder 142: 4)
      (VIII.15).
      One videotape recording of a television interview with Vitaly Shentalinksky, author of a book on the fate of Babel and other literary figures under Stalin
    - "Isaak Babel," a film by Jack Janssen, New York, 1998 (Box-folder 143: 1)
      (VIII.16).
      One videotape recording, in Russian with English subtitles
    - "Jewish Luck," Moscow, 1925 (Folder 143: 2)
      (VIII.17).
      One videotape recording of a silent film, with Yiddish and English subtitles. Original Russian subtitles were written by Babel
    - Photocopy of a poster for the film, "Iskussstvo zhit' v Odesse," based on Babel's stories, n.d. (Folder 143: 3)
      (VIII.18)
    - Illustrated Books and Original Art, Boston, 2002 (Folder 143: 4)
      (VIII.19).
      Reproduces stills from a film for which Babel wrote the screenplay
    - "Jewish Short Stories from Eastern Europe and Beyond," National Yiddish Book Center, 1995 (Folder 143: 5)
      (VIII.20).
      Six audiocassette recordings of short stories by various East European authors, including four by Babel. In English
  - Photography, 1921-1997. (Box 144)
    Prints, serial issue, and monographs, relating to Babel and his milieu
    - Eight prints depicting Russian cavalry officers and soldiers, including Savitsky and Frunze circa 1921-1922, and one print depicting a collage of the previous photographs (Folder 144: 1)
    - One Russian postcard with a photograph of Babel, Moscow, 1934 (Folder 144: 2)
    - Kupferberg, Tuli and Sylvia Topp, As They Were, New York, 1973 (Folder 144: 3)
      (IX.5).
      Includes reproduction of a photograph of Babel
    - Napplebaum, Moses, Our Age, Ann Arbor, 1984 (Folder 144: 4)
      (IX.6).
      Reproduces a photograph of Babel
    - King, David, The Commissar Vanishes: The Falsification of Photographs and Art in Stalin's Russia, New York, 1997 (Folder 144: 5)
      (IX.7).
      Reproduces the last known photographs of Babel, in Lubyanka prison, Moscow, c. 1939 May
    - London Review of Books, 1990 April 5 (Folder 144: 6)
      (IX.8).
      Cover reproduces a photograph of Babel, from the David King collection, n.d.
  - Collections, exhibitions, conferences, 1986-2000.; See also oversize and miscellaneous materials, box 148, for one item
    Catalogs, monographs, and serial issues, relating to Babel and his milieu.
    - Odesskii gosudarstvennyi literaturnyi muzei: Putevoditel', Odessa, 1986 (Folder 144: 7)
      (X.1)
    - Kurochkin, Iu., Knizhnye vstrechi, Moscow, 1988 (Folder 144: 8)
      (X.2)
    - Knigi I rukopisi v sobranii M. S. Lesmana, Moscow, 1989 (Folder 144: 9)
      (X.3)
    - Isaac Emmanuilovich Babel (1894-1940): The Collection of Irwin T. and Shirley Holtzman, Ann Arbor, 1994 (Box-folder 145: 1)
      (X.4).
      Two copies of checklist of exhibit
    - Pervye Babelevskie chteniia, Odessa, 1989 (Folder 145: 2)
      (X.5).
    - Babel Centennial Conference, Gorky Institute, Moscow, 1994 June 6-9
      - Invitation and program (Folder 145: 3)
        (X.6).
        In Russian
      - Catalog (Folder 145: 4)
        (X.7).
      - Exhibition catalog (Folder 145: 5)